Guide to the Roderick S. French papers, 1969-2013 MS2296.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Roderick S. French papers
1969-2013
1969-1998
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2296.UA
2 Linear Feet 4 document boxes
This collection contains the personal papers of Dr. Roderick S. French, former faculty member and admnistrator at The George Washington University. Dr. French served as Associate Director and Director of the University's Division of Experimental Programs for fifteen years, and as Vice President for Academic Affairs for eleven years. The collection includes notes, press releases, speeches, brochures, correspondence, clippings, reports, and publications pertaining to Dr. Roderick S. French's work for The George Washington University, and his involvement in the D.C. Council of Humanities, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the American University of Sharjah, and other organizations. Materials in this collection date from 1969 to 2013, with the bulk of the material dating between 1969 and 1998.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Roderick S. French, 2011 (2011.045). Additional gift, 2014 (2014.040)
Arrangement
Organized into 6 series: Biographical Information; Division of Experimental Programs; Humanities Work, National Activities, and Publications; Vice President for Academic Affairs; University Honors Program; American University of Sharjah, United Arab Emirates
Related Materials
An oral history interview with Dr. French, conducted in 2011 by Assistant University Archivist Ashley Locke, is available in the University Archives Oral History collection, MS0371.
Records for the office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs are located in RG0004.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Roderick S. French served The George Washington University for twenty-eight years as a faculty member and administrator.
Dr. French earned an A.B. in philosophy from Kenyon College, an M.Div. in church history, theology and biblical studies from the Episcopal Theological School in Cambridge, Massachusetts, an S.T.M. in Modern church history from Union Theological Seminary in New York City, and a Ph.D. in American Civilization from The George Washington University. French began his career as the Executive Director of the Youth Department of the World Council of Churches in Geneva (1959-64). He later served as Special Assistant to the Director of the Office of Public Affairs of the Peace Corps from 1967 to 1968.
Dr. French joined The George Washington University as a Ph.D. student in 1968 and was appointed as the Associate Director of the University's Division of Experimental Programs in 1969. He was made director of the Division in 1979, and was responsible for university-wide curricular innovation and academic program development. In 1984 he was made Vice President for Academic Affairs, a position he held until 1995 when he stepped down to work with the University Honors Program. Dr. French left GW in 1997 to become the First Chancellor of the American University of Sharjah in the United Arab Emirates. He served as Chancellor Emeritus of the American University of Sharjah, a member of its Board of Trustees, and secretary of the Board of Directors of the AUS-USA Foundation. He retired as Chancellor in the summer of 2002.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains notes, press releases, speeches, brochures, correspondence, clippings, reports, and publications pertaining to Dr. Roderick S. French's work for The George Washington University, and his involvement in the D.C. Council of Humanities, the National Endowment for the Humanities, the American University of Sharjah, and other organizations. Materials in this collection date from 1969 to 2013, with the bulk of the material dating between 1969 and 1998.
United States -- District of Columbia -- Washington; Education, Higher -- United States; Humanities; Education; George Washington University. School of Public and International Affairs; United States. Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps; National Endowment for the Humanities; George Washington University. Office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs; George Washington University. Virginia Science and Technology Campus; George Washington University. Division of Experimental Programs; George Washington University; French, Roderick S., Dr.
- Biographical Information, 2007-2011; Series 1; 2 folder(s)
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes autobiographical essays and resumes of Dr. Roderick S. French. Materials date from 2007 to 2011, but the essays focus on the period between 1969 and 1998.
  - Background, 2007-2011; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Background Notes for 1968-1984, 2011; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Division of Experimental Programs, 1969-1974; Series 2; 3 folder(s)
  This series contains press releases, speeches, brochures, correspondence, and reports pertaining to Dr. French's work for The George Washington University's Division of Experimental Programs. Materials date from 1969 to 1974.
  - Division of Experimental Programs - Curricular Innovation, circa 1969-1984; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Division of Experimental Programs - Initiatives in D.C. History, 1973-1980; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Participation in Alumni Events, 1972-1974; Series 2 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Humanities Work, National Activities, and Publications, 1973-1989; Series 3; 6 folder(s)
  This series contains notes, programs, articles, publications, brochures, speeches, and correspondence pertaining to Dr. French's activities related to the Humanities and scholarly publication. Included are materials about the D.C. Humanities Council and the awarding of a National Endowment for the Humanities Challenge Grant to The George Washington University. The series also contains a eulogy delivered by French in honor of Professor Letitia Brown. Documents date between 1973 and 1998.
  - D.C. Humanities Council, 1979-1986; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - NEH Challenge Grant, 1980-1984; Series 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Activities, 1977-1985; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Scholarly Publications, 1979-1989; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National Humanities Roles, 1988-1997; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Professional Publications, 1988-1998; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Vice President for Academic Affairs, 1984-2013; 1984-1997; Series 4; 45 folder(s)
  This series contains records related to Dr. French's service as Vice President for Academic Affairs at The George Washington University. Included are notes, speeches, clippings, correspondence, and publications dating between 1984 and 2013. Topics include the reorganization of the School of International Affairs, research, the Virginia Science and Technology campus, the Naval ROTC unit on campus, orientation for new department chairs, equal opportunity and diversity, the anniversary of the first doctoral degree awarded by the university, the School of Educational and Human Development, and the Humanities.
  - Press Release for Appointment as Vice President for Academic Affairs, 19 January 1984; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Addresses to Faculty Assemblies, 1984-1988; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Speeches to Fall Convocations, 1985; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Speeches to Honors Convocations, 1984-1987; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Speeches at Graduate School of Arts and Sciences Ph.D. Hooding Ceremonies, 1986-1988; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, 1981-1988; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes speeches for the annual lunch for new Emeriti faculty, annual orientations for new department chairs, a speech concerning equal opportunity and diversity, a speech for the 100th anniversary of doctoral programs at GW, and a speech for the annual School of Education and Human Development alumni gathering.
  - Notes for Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1984-1988; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Reorganization of the School of International Affairs, 1987; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Research, 1986; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Northern Virginia Campus, 1985-1988; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Naval ROTC Unit, 1984-1987; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Items in Campus Publications, 1984-1987; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous, 1987-1988; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Annual Reports to President Trachtenberg, 1988-1995; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Assembly Addresses, 1988-1991; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Talks at Fall Convocations and at Honors Convocations, 1989-1995; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Talks at Ph.D. Hooding Ceremonies, 1989-1995; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Talks for Annual Lunches for New Emeriti, 1989-1995; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1988-1989; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1989-1990; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1990-1991; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1991-1992; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1992-1993; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1993-1994; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1994-1995; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous Campus Talks, 1996-1997; Series 4 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Research, 1988-1994; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Graduate Studies, 1992; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Classified Research, 1989-1990; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Policy Studies, 1992; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - School of Public Health & Health Sciences, 2002-2003; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reorganization of Arts & Sciences, 1990; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Trustee Mandated Review of SEAS, 1993-1995; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Northern Virginia Campus, 1989-1994; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Budget Planning Documents, 1989-1993; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Diversity: Gender, Race, Nationality, 1989-1995; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - University Teaching Center, 1990-1995; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - NROTC, 1989-1990; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Board of Trustees, 1988-1994; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - University Professors, 1990-1997; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - University Seminars - General, 1994-1997; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - University Seminar on the Idea of the University in the 21st Century, 1997; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Items in Campus Publications, 1989-1995; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - On Stepping Down, 1995; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Lloyd Elliott's Memorial Service Eulogy, 26 February 2013; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- University Honors Program, 1995-1997; Series 5; 1 folder(s)
  This series contains records related to Dr. French's involvement with the University Honors Program at the George Washington University from 1995-1997.
  - Honors Program, 1996-1997; Series 5 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- American University of Sharjah, United Arab Emirates, 1997-2002; Series 6; 1 folder(s)
  This series contains materials related to Dr. French's involvement with the American University of Sharjah. Dr. French served as the First Chancellor of the American University of Sharjah in the United Arab Emirates from 1997 to 2002. He also served as a member of its Board of Trustees and secretary of the Board of Directors of the AUS-USA Foundation. The materials date from 1997 to 2002.
  - American University of Sharjah (UAE), 1997-2002; Series 6 (Box 4, Folder 22)